Register of the Maxwell McGaughey Hamilton Papers, 1916-1957
Hoover Institution Archives
Maxwell McGaughey Hamilton papers,
1916-1957
XX079
Hamilton, Maxwell McGaughey, 1896-1957
4 manuscript boxes (1.7 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Reports, memoranda, correspondence, lectures, press releases, and printed matter, relating to American foreign policy toward China, Japan, and other government officials concerning economic and political conditions in Japan and Manchuria, 1933-1934.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
United States. Dept. of State.; China.; China--Economic conditions--1912-1949.; China--Foreign relations--United States.; China--Politics and government--1912-1949.; Finland.; Finland--Foreign relations--United States.; Japan.; Japan--Economic conditions--1918-1945.; Japan--Foreign relations--United States.; Japan--Politics and government--1912-1945.; Manchuria--Economic conditions.; Manchuria--Politics and government.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Foreign relations--China.; United States--Foreign relations--Finland.; United States--Foreign relations--Japan.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Diplomats--United States.
Biographical Note
1896, December 20 Born, Tahlequah, Oklahoma
1918 Litt. B., Princeton University
1920-1924 Student interpreter in U.S. Legation in China
1924-1927 U.S. Consular Service in China
1927-1931 Assigned to Division of Far Eastern Affairs, U.S. Department of State
1931-1937 Assistant Chief, Division of Far Eastern Affairs
1937-1943 Chief, Division of Far Eastern Affairs
1943-1944 Minister Counselor in U.S. Embassy in U.S.S.R.
1944 Special Assistant to Secretary of State
1945-1947 U.S. Minister to Finland
1949 Appointed chairman, Far Eastern Commission
Series Description
- DIPLOMATIC CORRESPONDENCE, 1916-1921 (?) (Box 1)
  Register of correspondence between U.S. Legation in China and Chinese Foreign Ministry, 1916-1921 (?), in Chinese with English translation.
- TRIP TO FAR EAST, 1933-1934: DIARY AND REPORTS (Box 1)
  Diary and reports of visit to Japan, China, Hong Kong, and the Philipines, September 1933 -February 1934, undertaken by Maxwell H. Hamilton as a U.S. State Department official, arranged as listed.
- LECTURES, 1932-1944 (Box 1)
  Copies of lectures delivered by Maxwell M. Hamilton, arranged chronologically.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1917-1957 (Boxes 1-4)
  Correspondence, reports, memoranda, press releases, clippings, newsletters, maps, and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject.
- DECLASSIFIED RECORDS, 1950 (Box 4)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover.
Container List
- DIPLOMATIC CORRESPONDENCE, 1916-1921 (?)
  - Register of correspondence between U.S. Legation in China and Chinese Foreign Ministry, 1916-1921 (?) in Chinese, with English translation (Box 1)
- TRIP TO FAR EAST, 1933-1934: DIARY AND REPORTS
  - Diary of visit to Japan, China, Hong Kong, and the Philippines, September 1933-February 1934, undertaken for U.S. State Department, with summaries of interviews with U.S. and foreign officials and other individuals. Includes indexes to interviews (Box 1)
  - Reports of findings on political and economic conditions in the Far East, resulting from visit to Japan, China, Hong Kong, and the Philippines, September 1933-February 1934, with cover letter to Cordell Hull, March 20, 1934
- LECTURES, 1932-1944
  - "China in 1931," Army War College, April 5, 1932 (Box 1)
  - "Recent Developments in China," Army War College, March 9, 1933
  - "The Situation in the Far East," Army War College, January 12, 1935
  - "The Far East," Army War College, Dcember 10, 1935
  - "The Far Eastern Situation," Army War College, January 7, 1937
  - "The Situation in the Far East," Army War College, January 10, 1938
  - "The Situation in the Far East," Army War College, January 6, 1939
  - "The Situation in the Far East," Army War College, January 9, 1940
  - "Coordination between the Political and Military Branches of the Government - with Special Reference to Activities in the Field," Army and Navy Staff College, December 30, 1944
- SUBJECT FILE, 1917-1957
  - Bibliographies on Far East and U.S.S.R. (Box 1)
  - China
    - General
    - 1949-1955
    - Finance, 1941-1945
    - Relations with U.S.S.R.
  - Communism
    - Life under communism series, 1953
  - Finland (Box 2)
    - General, 1947-1956
    - Foreign Relations, 1952-1957
  - Formosa, 1950-1955
  - Great Britain, Foreign Policy on U.S.S.R., 1946-1951
  - India, Politics and Society, 1940
  - Japan
    - General
      - 1945-1955
      - 1937-1940
    - Economy, 1953-1957
    - Far Eastern Commission
      - General, 1946-1952
      - Rosters, 1949-1951
    - Peace Treaty and U.S. Security Treaty 1951-1952 (Box 3)
    - Relations with U.S.S.R., 1955-1956
  - Korea and Korean War
  - Land reform
  - Miscellaneous
  - Philippines
    - Economy, 1950-1952
  - U.S. Foreign Policy
    - General, 1941-1957
    - China, to 1949
    - Far East
      - General, 1932-1957
      - Conference Proceedings, 1957
    - Japan (Box 4)
      - 1937-1941
        - General
        - Letter to Joseph C. Grew, July 28, 1939
      - 1945-1955
    - U.S.S.R., 1948-1953
  - U.S.S.R., 1917-1956
- DECLASSIFIED RECORDS, 1950 (Box 4)
  - 2011 September release of records, 1950 (Box 4)
    Memos and reports relating to Pacific area matters